Guide to the John Dallas Langston Papers, 1842-1969 (bulk 1941-1946)
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
John Dallas Langston papers 1842-1969, bulk 1941-1946
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Langston, John Dallas, 1881-1963
13.2 linear feet Extent: 9,900 Items
U.S. Army colonel from North Carolina. Bound volumes, correspondence, scrapbooks, and clippings detailing Langston's activities as a Trinity College (later became Duke University) student, then later as a U.S. Army colonel in World War II, and assistant to General Lewis B. Hershey on the Selective Service Board. Langston also served on General E. H. Crowder's draft board in Washington, D.C. during World War I: Crowder was chiefly responsible for drafting of the Selective Service Act which was passed in May 1917, and as Provost Marshal General had responsibility for administering the program during the war. The bulk of the material covers the period 1941-1946. Other items provide evidence for Langston's support of Prohibition, and his role as opponent of Al Smith in the N.C. Democratic primary in 1928. Later additions to the collection document earlier Langston family history. They also contain Langston's poems, and correspondence with Professor Edwin Mims about them, a scrapbook of the Simmons-Bailey campaign for the U.S. Senate in 1930, and his correspondence with New York attorney Roscoe S. Conkling concerning Langston's opposition to compulsory military service during peacetime.
RL.00797
Language: Material in English
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48 hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The John Dallas Langston Papers were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library in 1949.
Collection Overview
Bound volumes, correspondence, scrapbooks, and clippings detailing Langston's activities as a Trinity College (later became Duke University) student, then later as a U.S. Army colonel in World War II, and assistant to General Lewis B. Hershey on the Selective Service Board. Langston also served on General E. H. Crowder's draft board in Washington, D.C. during World War I: Crowder was chiefly responsible for drafting of the Selective Service Act which was passed in May 1917, and as Provost Marshal General had responsibility for administering the program during the war. The bulk of the material covers the period 1941-1946. Other items provide evidence for Langston's support of Prohibition, and his role as opponent of Al Smith in the N.C. Democratic primary in 1928. Later additions to the collection document earlier Langston family history. They also contain Langston's poems, and correspondence with Professor Edwin Mims about them, a scrapbook of the Simmons-Bailey campaign for the U.S. Senate in 1930, and his correspondence with New York attorney Roscoe S. Conkling concerning Langston's opposition to compulsory military service during peacetime.
Subject Headings
Hershey, Lewis Blaine, 1893-; Crowder, E. H. (Enoch Herbert), 1859-1932; Simmons, Furnifold M. (Furnifold McLendel), 1854-1940; Bailey, Josiah William, 1873-1946; Mims, Edwin, 1872-1959; Conkling, Roscoe S. (Roscoe Seely), 1884-1956; Langston family; Trinity College (Durham, N.C.) -- History; Duke University -- History; Draft -- United States -- History -- 20th century; Prohibition -- United States -- History
Contents of Collection
- Papers, 1842-1969 (bulk 1941-1946), (30 boxes)
  - Memoranda to all officers, 1941-1946 (Box 1)
  - Memoranda to all division chiefs, 1941-1945 (Box 1)
  - Memoranda to all employees, 1941-1945 (Box 1)
  - Advice to all officers, telegrams, 1943-1944 (Box 1)
  - Flag memos to General Hershey, 1946 (Box 1)
  - Langston's Commonplace Book (Box 2)
  - Langston's special miscellaneous files, 1942-1946 (Box 2)
  - Speeches, addresses and lectures delivered by Colonel Langston (Box 2)
  - Reminiscences and biographical sketch (Box 3)
  - Legal papers, 1842-1954 (Box 3)
  - Miscellany (Box 3)
  - Newspaper clippings (Box 3)
  - Pamphlets and printed material (Box 3)
  - Pictures (Box 3)
  - Correspondence, 1970 (Box 4)
  - Clippings, 1941-1946 (Box 4)
  - Map (Box 4)
  - Clippings, 1966-1969 (Box 5)
  - Correspondence, 1903-1963 (Box 6)
  - Work or Fight (Box 7)
  - Universal Military Training (Box 7)
  - Universal Military Training Committee, final report on assignments of 1944 Aug. 2 (Box 7)
  - Planning Council
    - organization and recommendation (Box 7)
    - Scrapbook (Box 7)
  - National headquarters organization (Box 7)
  - Tables of organization from national headquarters and state headquarters (Box 7)
  - Directors report, 1941-1945 (Box 7)
  - Addresses, lectures and speeches (Box 7)
  - Policy determinations, 1943-1945 (Box 8)
  - Rescinded policy determinations, 1943-1945 (Box 8)
  - Officer personnel (active), 1941-1945 (Box 8)
  - Officer personnel, 1898-1944 (Box 8)
  - Personnel assigned to state headquarters, 1944-1945 (Box 8)
  - Selective Service clippings, general, 1944 Sept. 11-1945 Nov. (Box 9)
  - Correspondence, personal, 1950-1954 (Box 10)
  - Important letters, 1918-1949 (Box 10)
  - Correspondence with Bruce Crave, 1928-1940 (Box 10)
  - Correspondence with David A. Lockmiller, re. Enoch H. Crowder biography, 1919-1955 (Box 10)
  - Monthly statistics, 1944-1945 (Box 11)
  - Statistics, personal, confidential, 1940-1943 (Box 11)
  - Miscellaneous statistics, 1941-1945 (Box 11)
  - Civilian public service camps, statistical report, 1941-1946 (Box 11)
  - Regulations (Box 12)
  - Amended and rescinded regulations (Box 12)
  - Important memoranda, 1940-1945 (Box 13)
  - Digest of significant memoranda, 1942-1944 (Box 13)
  - Administrative memoranda, 1941-1946 (Box 14)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 15)
  - News digest, 1940 (Box 16)
  - News digest and editorial comments, 1944-1945 (Box 16)
  - Presidential appeals, organization (Box 17)
  - Statistics on presidential appeals compiled by R and S (Box 17)
  - Weekly status report for presidential appeals, 1941-1946 (Box 17)
  - Selective Service statistical report of presidential appeals, 1942-1945 (Box 17)
  - Monthly statistical analysis and number appeals decided by classification, 1941-1946 (Box 17)
  - Newspaper clippings, general, 1945 Nov.-1946 May (Box 18)
  - Post war planning clippings, 1943 June-1945 Feb. (Box 18)
  - Clippings and interesting data on General Hershey (Box 18)
  - Local board memoranda, 1941-1946 (Box 18)
  - Selective Service presidential appeals, 1941-1945 (Box 19)
  - State director advice, memoranda to all state directors, 1942-1945 (Box 20)
  - State director advice, 1943-1946 (Box 20)
  - Miscellaneous memoranda to all state directors (Box 20)
  - Rescinded state director advices, 1941-1945 (Box 20)
  - Correspondence, Personal (Box 21)
    - 1905-1937, 1940 Aug.-1941 Aug. (Box 21)
    - 1940 Mar.-1950 Dec. (Box 22)
  - Selective Service report in reply to complaints of National Committee on Conscientious Objectors organized by the American Civil Liberties Union (Box 23)
  - Pertinent data pertaining to conscientious objectors and Jehovah's Witnesses (Box 23)
  - Conscientious objectors, report on Civil Liberties' Union complaints (Box 23)
  - Pertinent data pertaining to ministers of religion (Box 23)
  - Legal opinions (Box 23)
  - Legal opinion file,1944-1945 (Box 23)
  - Studies in post war training (Box 23)
  - Selective Service extension course, 1935 (Box 23)
  - Selective Service studies, 1935-1940 (Box 23)
  - Stayback File, 1943 Mar.-1946 May (Box 24)
  - Selective Service clippings, general, 1943 Jan.-1944 Sept. (Box 25)
  - Stayback File, 1935 Feb.-1943 Feb. (Box 26)
  - Correspondence, personal, 1925-1954 (Box 27)
  - Printed material (Box 28-30)
- Addition 1987, (2 boxes)
  - Volumes 1-7 (Box 1)
    - Early Life (Box 1)
    - World War I (Box 1)
    - Lt. Gov. Race (1928) (Box 1)
    - Prohibition (Box 1)
    - World War II (Box 1)
  - Volumes 8-13 (Box 2)
    - World War II (Box 2)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 2)
- Manuscript Volume Series
  - Scrapbook (Box 31)
- Additional Materials
  - Clipping, 1968 (Box 31, Folder In Small Collections:)